<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Noble Blastus the honor of a lord chamberlaine: and of a good bed-chamber--man: or The courtier justified in conditions of peace. Being a sermon preacht the 27. of March, 1631. before Sir Lucius Cary, and the congregation at Burford Church in Oxfordshire; with speciall relation to the Coronation-day, and the plague and dearth then among the people. By Iohn Randol Bachelor in Divinitie, of Brasen-nose Colledge in Oxford.</title>
            <author>Randal, John, b. 1594 or 5.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1633</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10400</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20684</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115627</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850845</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850845</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16076</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10400)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16076)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1002:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Noble Blastus the honor of a lord chamberlaine: and of a good bed-chamber--man: or The courtier justified in conditions of peace. Being a sermon preacht the 27. of March, 1631. before Sir Lucius Cary, and the congregation at Burford Church in Oxfordshire; with speciall relation to the Coronation-day, and the plague and dearth then among the people. By Iohn Randol Bachelor in Divinitie, of Brasen-nose Colledge in Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Randal, John, b. 1594 or 5.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Bernard Alsop and Thomas Fawcett] for Tho: Lambert neare the Hospitall-gate in Smithfield,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1633.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printers' names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16076:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16076:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Noble Blaſtus:</p>
            <p>THE HONOR OF A LORD CHAMBERLAINE: AND OF A GOOD BED-CHAMBER-MAN: OR The COVRTIER juſtified in Conditions of Peace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BEING</hi> A Sermon preacht the 27. of March, 1631. before Sir LVCIVS CARY, and the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at <hi>Burford Church</hi> in <hi>Oxfordſhire;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WITH Speciall Relation to the Coronation-day, and the Plague and Dearth then among the people.</p>
            <p>BY IOHN RANDOL Bachelor in Divinitie, of <hi>Braſen-noſe Colledge</hi> in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho: Lambert</hi> neare the Hoſpitall-gate in Smithfield.
1633.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:16076:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16076:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ACTS. 12.20.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And <hi>Herod</hi> was highly diſpleaſed with them of Tyre and Sidon: but they came with one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord to him, and having made <hi>Blaſtus</hi> the Kings Chamberlaine their friend, deſired peace, becauſe their countrey was nouriſhed by the Kings countrey.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="body_of_sermon">
               <head>And <hi>Herod</hi> was war-minded or intending warre to the Tyrians and Sidonians: but they came with one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord to him; and perſwading <hi>Blaſtus,</hi> who was one o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Kings bed-chamber, or, of the Kings-bed-chamber, they deſired peace, becauſe their countrey was nouriſhed by the Kings.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His text conteineth a deſigne of King <hi>Herod:</hi> a deſigne of warre: And uſually deſignes of warre are in the ſpring; as now the ſeaſon is with us: deſignes of warre, which pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate men ought not to han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle; yet appertain to us all it doth to render thanks
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16076:3"/>for having ſo gracious a King of peace, in whom there is no deſigne of warre: virtues by their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries doe beſt appeare; the Kings grace by <hi>Herods</hi> bloody minde; the happineſſe of our peace by the unhappineſſe of <hi>Herods</hi> warre: therefore have I choſen this text to celebrate this day; a day of peace; wherein our Soveraigne Lord, a King of peace, beganne his raigne, for the good of other kingdomes aſwell as of our owne; becauſe hee is not hoſtilely intended againſt any realm: he is not, but God is: as we ſhall juſtly commemorate unto you, how God by famine hath deſigned a warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us all, unleſſe as the Tyrians ſought peace with <hi>Herod,</hi> ſo we with God: Thus is the text ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to remember us both of this preſent precious daye and of this preſent deare yeare: The parts are theſe:</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Herods</hi> deſigne againſt the <hi>Tyrians:</hi> 2. The <hi>Tyrians</hi> prevention of ſuch deſigne. The deſigne is for war; a paſſionate deſigne; he was not only an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with them of Tyre and Sidon, (as the former tranſlations did read it) but highly diſpleaſed with them; and more, (as the laſt tranſlation notes in the margent,) that
<hi>Herod</hi> did beare an hoſtile mind intending warre againſt them: as it is in the Greek,
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſaith <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> a war-minded man: <hi>pluſquam iratus,</hi> hee was more then angry; for hee did meditate a warre againſt them: <hi>bellum enim meditabatur,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Lintrenſis.</hi>) he had a fighting minde, and meditated warre againſt them: <hi>pugnacem gerens animum; meditans ac moliens belium,</hi> ſaith <hi>Lorinus:</hi> yes, yes; <hi>anim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> moliens bellum<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:16076:3"/>he was bent for war, ſaith the <hi>Tigurine:</hi> This is the firſt part:
<hi>Herods</hi> deſigne againſt the <hi>Tyrians</hi> and <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donians.</hi> Then the ſecond part is their preventio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this deſign by pacifying the King: wherin obſerve their expeditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of redreſſe: they came preſently to the King: and their unanimity: they came with one accord: then their prudent and reſpective dealing, by a mediator; having made <hi>Blaſtus</hi> their friend: having perſwaded <hi>Blaſtus;</hi> who is deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by his office, to be one of the Kings bed-cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, or one over the Kings bed-chamber; by whoſe meanes they preferre their ſubmiſſive requeſt to the King himſelfe for peace, by way of petition they deſired peace; and laſtly the cauſe of all; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their countrey was nouriſht by the Kings countrey: there's cauſe enough for their deſirance of peace; but his deſire of warre hath no mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned cauſe at all: we are to examine the conjectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall doctrines of both ſides: beginning with King <hi>Herod,</hi> and his paſſionate deſigne for warre <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> he was wrathfully minded to make warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them.</p>
               <div n="Herod's passion" type="section">
                  <head>Of Herod and his paſsion.</head>
                  <p>When iniquity runnes in a line, tranſgreſſion downe a whole blood; in ſome generations you ſhall ſcarce finde any good of all the name: <hi>Herod</hi> the ſon of <hi>Antipater</hi> ſlew all the yonger innocents when Chriſt was borne; and would have murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red our Saviour too; if providence had not preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16076:4"/>it by a ſaving dreame. <hi>Herod,</hi> his ſonne, <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarch of Galilee,</hi> ſlew <hi>Iohn the Baptiſt Mar.</hi> 6. and moſt deſpitefully uſed our Saviour at his death: <hi>Luke</hi> 23. and this third <hi>Herod</hi> in the text ſlew
<hi>Iames</hi> the Apoſtle, empriſoned <hi>Peter,</hi> drew his own Traine-band to execution; and now is in a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan ague of choler and melancholy mixt with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did blood, untill he have laid the <hi>Tyrians</hi> diſhono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably at his feet. Among <hi>Ieroboams</hi> race, one yong man was found, 1 <hi>Kings.</hi> 14.13. that had pious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions toward God: and it was but onely one: But among the <hi>Herods</hi> none.</p>
                  <p>In mariage then be carefull with what race yee interveine: <hi>Fortes creantur fortibus,</hi> Gracious men of gracious parents come; and cruell impes from bloody loynes: if otherwiſe, it is by chance: <hi>Lois</hi> was good, <hi>Eunice</hi> good, <hi>Timotheus</hi> good; S. <hi>Paul</hi> brings downe the line: Grand-parents, <hi>parents,</hi> children, all good: 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5.
<hi>Ariſtotle</hi> can ſit yee with a contrary tale; wherein the grandfather was evill, the father evill, and the ſonne evill: A plea being entred againſt a man for beating of his own father, he thus anſwers to defend himſelfe; Moſt honourable Judges, in regard my father beate my Grandfather before he dyed, and mine owne ſon hath likewiſe beaten me, let it not ſeeme ſo hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous a crime unto your ſacred eares, if I have bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten my father alſo; <hi>eſt enim hoc generi noſtro propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um:</hi> For it is the property of all our generation to beate their fathers, ſometime or other, before they die. A goodly property.</p>
                  <p>Another drawing his father by the head unto
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16076:4"/>the utmoſt doore, his Father intreated him there to reſt; for ſo far he drew his Father, and left him there: <hi>Ariſt.</hi> lib. 7. <hi>Eth.</hi> cap. 6. a chapter and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples ſuting with theſe <hi>Herods</hi> beſt of any next unto the word of God: for they were <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> angry men by nature; and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> quickly angry by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance; and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> deeply, and bitterly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry unto warre, and blood and death it ſelfe: Men full of revenge, and of greater miſchiefe full: This was the property of all their generation: Heavens bleſſe women from ſuch husbands, men from ſuch a Prince, as
<hi>Herod</hi> was: <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> a man ſuddenly inflamed with anger; meditating nothing but war and death upon every light ſuſpition of offence: <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>Yet was not he the chiefe Commander of the State; but an underling deputie, or Lieutenant on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly:
<hi>Regunculus;</hi> a vaſſall-King: <hi>Claudius Caeſar</hi> was the chiefe Emperour of all Judaea, and the world beſides: <hi>Herod</hi> a contemptible man in compariſon of him; of an obſcure fortune in <hi>Caligulaes</hi> time, caſt into priſon but a while agoe; and now his bolts being newly knockt off, and the fury toſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch honour, as you ſee; he ſwells &amp; domineeres over all; as if he were the ſupreme Governour himſelfe.</p>
                  <p>There is nothing more terrible then a Humble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bee; if it could but get a ſting. Set ſervants on horſeback once, they will quickly make their mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters go on foot. A ſporting feaſt in was among the Theſſalians and the Romans themſelves at their Saturnalian feaſtes, for the Maſters once a yeare
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16076:5"/>to ſerve their men; and the Roman Matrons to wayte upon their maides; obeying each command as they did theirs the day before: <hi>Macrob. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 7.10.12.
<hi>Seneca epiſt.</hi> 4.7. Whether a wanton, or a wiſer order; to acknowledge fortunes chance, the charity of nature, or the change of times, I do not know: But ſure I am, King
<hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeakes it in a ſerious crime, amongſt the many vanities of this World, that he had ſeene this abſurdity for one, Servants riding on horſeback and Princes walking beneath on foot: <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.10. A vanity for ſlaves to be ſeen above their betters; thoſe on horſeback, theſe on foote: but an abſurdity of vanities to ſee them higher in their owne imaginations, then they were upon the ſaddle: For he ſaw them not on Aſſes, or on mules as Princes of that Country rode; But on horſes; the proudeſt, fierceſt, ſwifteſt executioner of ſtate: to ſignifie their ſuperſtately pride. And ſuch this <hi>Herod</hi> was. For out of priſon did he come to reigne: and therefore ſhould have conſidered, ſaith <hi>Solomon, Eccleſ.</hi> 4.14. that from his reigne he might returne to priſon againe: God can empriſon Kings, as eaſily as they can other men: and therefore <hi>Herod</hi> needed not have been ſo too too outragiouſly forward for a war.</p>
                  <p>Meaneneſſe of beginning, or breach of greater Fortune, if once it come unto the priſon, or neere the pit; it ſhould teach more gentleneſſe to men and more obedience unto God: as it did
<hi>Manaſſeh</hi> in 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 33. <hi>v.</hi> 12: then God takes off their fetters, forgives their ſinnes, and will prolong their lives: But if they deſpiſe the puniſhment of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16076:5"/>God, remaine as obdurate as they were, ſudden deſtruction ſhall ſeize upon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſaith <hi>Iob</hi> moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetically in his 36. chap. v, 8: 9. &amp;c. as here on
<hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> moſt unexpectedly it did; becauſe hee was <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> a man of a bloudy and an hoſtile minde: upon every light occaſion meditating a warre: a man ſo meanely deſcended, and yet ſo highly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended againe in his owne conceit. And ſuch are uſually more fierce then antient blood: <hi>Aſperius nihil eſt humili, quum ſurgit in altum:</hi> their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance makes them more ſavage then the reſt: Or elſe their not partaking with the native blood: <hi>cuncta ferit, dum cuncta timet; deſaevit in omnes, ut ſe poſſe putent:</hi> as <hi>Claudianus</hi> goes on: he ſtrikes at all, where ever he feares; and rages againſt all, that all may thinke him alone to be the mighty man: whereas, love is the beſt preſerver of a State; feare is but a doubtfull band: <hi>ac multos metuat oportet, quem metuunt multi: Plut:</hi> and he muſt needs feare many, whom ſo many feare: meekeneſſe becomes the ſtart of honour beſt, ſo ſhall he be the ſooner pittied and befriended if he fall: but unſkilfull ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants thinke pride and fierceneſſe the onely two, can make them ſeeme to be egregious men: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides theſe privitive there are ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y poſitive cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, why ſuch as theſe may incline to vehement affections; eſpecially ariſing from a meane eſtate; and yet made forgetfull from whence they did ariſe; For as courſeſt corne affords the hardeſt cruſt; ſo courſeſt blood the moſt malignant cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler: their unuſuall dyet makes them inſolently mad; their company much more: inraged with fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16076:6"/>wines, and ſwolne venemouſly big with the flatteries of many men, having proſpered in a cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty or two. What dares not he now enterpriſe? <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> he was highly diſpleaſed to the very point of death it ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>Fooliſh men ſucceeding well twice or thrice in the ſhedding of blood are preſently drunke with everlaſting hope, that they ſhall ever proſper in it to their dying day.
<hi>Iames</hi> he beheaded, <hi>Peter</hi> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, executed his trayne-band; and faring well in that <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> he was bloodily and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilely intended for any occaſion that ſhould next accrew: But wiſe men know Gods patience doth invite them to repentance or their greater fall: it was <hi>Herods</hi> imperfection to gather fleſh, and take degrees in blood; yet never feare a fall; untill it was too late.</p>
                  <p>Some deputies are fiercer then ſupreme go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors themſelves, onely to demonſtrate their officiouſneſſe of place: others to ſatisfie the vengeance of their ſpleene: King
<hi>David</hi> would have <hi>Abner</hi> ſaved 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3. But <hi>Ioab</hi> the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the Army would have him ſlaine: <hi>Herod</hi> did deſtroy the innocent young children which Caeſar the chiefe Emperor would not have done: and therefore thus reproacht him for it, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he heard the newes: <hi>Herod</hi> thou art kinder to thy ſwine, then to thy ſonne: Thou killſt not them, becauſe thou art a Jew; but children all; thou doſt not ſpare thine owne; for feare of uſurpation, whilſt thou art alive.</p>
                  <p>The Divell brought our Saviour to the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16076:6"/>top; yet would not throw him downe: his owne Countrey men brought him to their ſteepeſt hill, and there they would have thruſt him head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long downe: <hi>Luke</hi> 4.
<hi>v.</hi> 29. No fire would our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour have from heaven to deſtroy the Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans; but his Diſciples would. <hi>Luke</hi> 9. as in the text: No warre would Caeſar have with them of Tyre; but his Lieutenant <hi>Herod</hi> hath a minde unto it: Whether in folly of too much officiouſneſſe, or in blood and covetiſme, as more likely it was: what ever pretenſes are, the cauſe is alwaies fowle; when under-officers are more fierce and bloody, then the ſupreme governours themſelves.</p>
                  <p>But what ayleth this tempeſtuous wolfe, that ſpeakes not a ſyllable leſſe then death? thinkes not a thought inferiour to warre? A warre ſpends both the blood and treaſure of a State: and therefore the State ſhould be conſulted with, before he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize a warre: <hi>Ph. Com. lib.</hi> 10. eſpecially the chiefe Moderator of the State: Caeſar, the imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will be yours; whatever your under-officers do offend: <hi>Herod,</hi> you may rule their treaſure, but not their hearts; if thus you eſtrange them by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary warres: your chronicles
<hi>Herod</hi> can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme you well by King <hi>Amaſiahs</hi> and <hi>Ioſiahs</hi> reigne, what maine dammages do ſtill accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch unneceſſary warres.</p>
                  <p>Unluckie progreſſe then! For what? <hi>Herod</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming downe to celebrate the Playes of Caeſars health, ſome cunning braines at Caeſarea have found meanes to accuſe the Tyrians to him: what will you ſay, if <hi>Blaſtus</hi> himſelfe ſubornd the men
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16076:7"/>that did accuſe, &amp; now the ſame become a ſuitor for their peace? I ſay that <hi>Blaſtus</hi> was too good a man to do ſo bad an act: but if he ſhould; the cryme was <hi>Herods</hi> ſtill: For as he is worſe that doth infect his minde, then he that doth corrupt his blood: ſo it is his fault, that doth not looke to both: the greater crime w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> greater care avoid: the height of da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger lyes in war: the height both of ſin &amp; of diſgrace in blood: the angry waſpes and bees are full of ſtings; the King of Bees, ſaith
<hi>Seneca,</hi> hath none: <hi>ſolus ipſe rex aculeo caret:</hi> No more ſhould
<hi>Herod</hi> have.</p>
                  <p>Or, what will you ſay, if <hi>Herod</hi> never meant, yet did pretend a warre: to uncreſt the Tyrians pride, and ſo inrich himſelf? But the text ſayes not, that he was
<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> as a man intending warre; but <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> a man really meditating a warre in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed: and I ſay, both ſafety and honour it is for Kings to bee contented with their owne: to bee Kings over themſelves as well as other men; that is truely to be a King indeed.</p>
                  <p>Or, if any man ſay, the warre was intended be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe tribute was not paid; that defence is falſe: for ſuch their ſpeedy petitioning of peace with coſt; ſhewes either Tribute was not due from them, or if due, then it never was denyed.</p>
                  <p>Or what? if the Tyrians did receive S. <hi>Peter</hi> and his doctrine with triumphant joy, who ſo lately had diſpleaſed <hi>Herod,</hi> might he not therefore juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly threaten them a warre? what if they did? ſo did the Caeſareans receive S. <hi>Peter</hi> too: why then ſhould he meditate a warre againſt thoſe, more then theſe? theſe under his Empire were, thoſe not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16076:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſo: if therefore againſt the Caeſareans he did not move a war for interteining of S. <hi>Peters</hi> faith; much leſſe againſt the Tyrians ought it to be done: as learnedly <hi>Zanchius</hi> and <hi>Lorinus</hi> againſt <hi>Baronius</hi> prove: What Prince did ever move a warre againſt thoſe that were not under his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand meerely &amp; only for religion ſake? for other things they may: but meerely and only for religion ſake,
<hi>Lorinus</hi> in his conſcience thinkes they may not. <hi>Lor. de fide &amp; Bello.</hi> So thinke our Church; who never do deſtroy an heretick meerely for religion ſake; but for ſome other additament of cauſe. No: no: their owne faire Chronicler <hi>Ioſephus,</hi> who deſcribes this very progreſſe of <hi>Herod</hi> to his death, reports no cauſe at all: and an unworthy warre it needs muſt be, that is not worthy of a cauſe. Nor do the Fathers give him any: but as S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſayes, becauſe he was <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> &amp;c. In
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>facile iraſcens &amp; vanae gloriae cupidus:</hi> a vaine glorious man; proud and ambitious; of a fierce &amp; overconfident mind; unſatiable both in wealth and honour: and where ſuch natures be; if no other cauſe be found, it is reaſon enough to move a warre upon you, meere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe you are next neighbour to them:
<hi>ſi ob nullam aliam cauſam, tamen propter vicinitatem:</hi> ô the miſerable condition of evill neighbourhood: it is the common infelicity of every age; that neighbours ſeldome doe agree: and the potenter they be, the greater ſtill the fewd: becauſe mighty men would ever dwell alone, ſaith <hi>Eſa. ch.</hi> 5.3. and being willing to fall out; though cauſe be wanting yet prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe is eaſie to be found: 'tis il to neighbour
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16076:8"/>next unto a covetous man; but worſe to border next unto an ambitious Prince: for as covetous me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> adde houſe to houſe; ſo tyrants realme to realme: no other kingdome is ſo great, but their appetite is as great, as it: ſtill thirſtingly extending their line over others though they have not ſo much as any juſt colour of a warre: thats the tyrants caſe: never contented prudently to rule their owne; though that bee greater charge then well they can performe: be their own dominions never ſo large, yet the next territory would make a ſweet addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to it: If <hi>Herod</hi> could but adde Tyre and Sidon to his kingdome of Judaea! for which hee is now <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> a man meditating of a war.</p>
                  <p>And is this thy meditation <hi>Herod?</hi> thou knowſt the law; if a meane man remove the marke of his Neighbours Land; he ſhall bee accurſed for it; much more a Prince if he,
<hi>Hoſea</hi> 5.10. the World it ſelfe is tranſitory: why then do you not enlarge your vertues rather then your lands? in coveting others goods, why will yee loſe your owne? your owne good conſcience, which ten thouſand times more pretious is, then all the gold of Tyre: know then to be contented whenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever yee have enough: know then yee have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough whenſoever yee are contented with it: though ye ſhed no blood, nor any combat wage; yet if you meditate or pretend a ſtrife to procure conditions of advantage to your ſelves by ruine of other men, that neither did offend God nor you the Caeleſtiall ſpirit will brand you for it, as he doth this
<hi>Herod</hi> in the text; that he was <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16076:8"/>man intending war or blood or any thing to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure unlawfull conditions of advantage to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>And is this thy meditation ſtill O <hi>Herod?</hi> and doſt thou proſper in it, after ſuch abundance of ſanctified blood as thou haſt ſhed? one would have thought, ſome thunderbolt might have daſht out thy braines, the earth have opened, and ſo the bloody wretch dropt downe at once, as Satan did, from heaven to hell, or that ſome potent enemy might have invaded well his land, and put him to the inglorious halter, or to the revengefull ſword. But loe proſperity in conditions of gain and peace! The wicked in their ſeaſons may have good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, be free from troubles others doe receive <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73. <hi>Ier.</hi> 12. Conjecture not the worſe of holineſſe, becauſe unholy men doe proſper in the world: they have their heaven here: till ſuddenly the ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of God take place; and then in a moment they tumble to the ground, ingloriouſly, as <hi>Herod</hi> did, conſumed of wormes: proud wormes-meat that we are, threatning a finall deſtruction unto others when we our ſelves are the very next to be deſtroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: Meteors, that blaze by night, and periſh the next faire morning with the riſing ſunne; vaine glorious fury, boile on, boile on, your blood is not yet hot enough, is it? ſet your heart on fire then, the very wilde fire of revenge. But is this a roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all paſſion fitting for a King? to be <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> upon every light occaſion the fomente of a warre? the diſmall iſſue ſhewes how vile it is with God: The wormes within a moneth encounter him to death:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16076:9"/>Though juſt warres be neceſſary to repreſſe bold ſinnes, yet unjuſt are odious both to God and men: <hi>Dij talem terris avertite peſtens:</hi> God in his good time take all ſuch <hi>Herods</hi> away from troubling of quiet men.</p>
                  <p>So much of <hi>Herod</hi> and his paſſionate intention of a warre: now come to the people againſt whom: <hi>the Tyrians and Sidonians:</hi> of them and their actions: Then <hi>Herod</hi> was hoſtilely intended againſt the Tyrians and Sidonians.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Tyre and Sidon" type="section">
                  <p>Tyre and Sidon two ancient townes upon the Siri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ſea, lay ſixe Germane miles apart, not far from <hi>Herods</hi> juriſdiction, <hi>Tyras</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Iaphet</hi> built the one: and Sidon, <hi>Hams</hi> grandchi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d, did found the other, if Divines may be beleeved: So that Tyre in likelihood might be the antienter: both mentioned <hi>Gen.</hi> 10. <hi>ver.</hi> 2. <hi>and ver.</hi> 15. But if hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens credit have, the Phaenicians built Sidon, then Tyre, and both before the Trojan warre: <hi>Iuſtin. lib.</hi> 18. <hi>Curtius</hi> ſayes, <hi>Agenor</hi> built them both: No matter which were the antienter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> both famous townes of merchandiſe they we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>; the Sidonians <hi>Homer</hi> celebrates for many-a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ted, many-crafted, and cunning-crafted men: <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and <hi>Virgill</hi> for the verſes or the kindreds ſake, <hi>Sidonia Dido:</hi> though <hi>Iuſtin</hi> ſay ſhee was born at Tyre: Famous Queene <hi>Dido,</hi> diſcontented at her huſhands death, fled into Africk; there built Carthage, and ſo renowned her ſexe, aſwell as name, that once a woman gat the third part of the world, <hi>Iuſtin. lib.</hi> 18. <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 2. at Tyre was <hi>Cad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:16076:9"/>borne, that did build Thebes: and, for ought we know, our ſelves might come from Tyre; at Tyre the art of navigation, and of making glaſſe; the ſiderall ſcience, and martiall diſcipline, with many other learned arts, their firſt invention had. The freedome and incomparable commodity of the ſea gave them variety of fame and fortune too: their youth they did diffuſe throughout all the world, and who but Tyre and Sidon, in all the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonies of Africk and Europe did beare the name? as <hi>Iuſtin, Curtius, Plinij, Mela,</hi> and others report at large.</p>
                  <p>But what need heathen authors? the ſacred text is full: and gives praecedency perpetually to Tyre: From Tyre did <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon</hi> fetch their Caedar for ſumptuous building of a Temple to the omnipotent God. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 2.3. Tyre was the Mart and fare for all the world: Fine wheat and ſpices; Unicornes hornes and Elephants teeth; lead iron and tynne, they were no traffick with them: But ſilk and purple; ſilver gold and pearle; the ſardius, topaze, and the diamond; the Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite and the onix; the jaſper ſapphire and the eme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raude, with every other pretions ſtone: their ſhops and garments were as rich below, as if they would compare with the pavement of the new Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem above the ſtarres: Read the 27. and 28 Chap. of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> and wonder, whether ever there were a ſtatelyer City in the world; then was this purple Tyre; this golden Tyre, nay, that is not enough, but this crowning Tyre: Queene of the ſeas, nay goddeſſe of the ſeas, whoſe merchants were princes
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16076:10"/>and their chapmen the Nobles of the world. Thou great creator of new Princes, where, and when thou pleaſeſt! Thou, whoſe very ſervants can ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteine ſuch loſſe of ponderous ſummes, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſenſible decay: as would make a Noble man of other Countryes ſhrink into his prime originall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine! As the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> doth deſcribe thine honour in termes as rich, as thou art proud, <hi>Eſay</hi> 23. Thou that feareſt Neptune more then God, or <hi>Alexander</hi> the great; haſt thou not yet beene of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten enough deſtroyed? Once did <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi> ruine all thy ſtate: another time <hi>Alexander</hi> the great: Thoſe Monarchs honoured thee in attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſuch a prize: And had the Romane Monarch Caeſar been thy foe; thou hadſt againe beene ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured here. But now tis <hi>Herod</hi> a vaſſall King. What is the cauſe between yee? or if not ſo; the pretenſe, what is it?</p>
                  <p>Monarchs and free Cities ſeldome doe agree, theſe to preſerve and magnifie their owne, invite the neighbour ſubjects to like freedome with themſelves: thoſe to maintaine their ambition and their luſt, ſtrive to enſlave the others like unto their owne: Embaſſadors, Agents and Merchants whoſoever you be, that traffique into other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealths, whoſe forme peradventure may dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from your owne; your licence is from God to preſerve each other, in exchanging friendſhipps, wealth, and wares: but no authority have you to deſtroy each others forme. The ſtately melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly comes aſwell from God, as doth the ſanguine mirth: Monarchs as lawfull as free cities are, free
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16076:10"/>cities as legitimate as they: I ſpeake for ſervants faith, that they be not
<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> medlers in other Princely governments, where they have nothing to doe: Preſerve your owne then; let others look to theirs, preſerving is good, but over-magnifying ruines all, as Tyre and Sidon here were like to do: For which <hi>Herod</hi> was hoſtilely intended againſt the Tyrians and Sidonians.</p>
                  <p>The greater riches are the greater prey: by armes that cannot, by ſubmiſſion muſt defend themſelves: Your riches, Tyre, and want of armes are your deſtruction now; unleſſe you doe ſubmit: it is better to want wealth then government of wealth: For which <hi>Herod</hi> was hoſtilely intended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Tyrian and Sidonian Townes.</p>
                  <p>There is a truer God of Tyre then they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: their pride and covetouſneſſe, their falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood in their wares; the true God of Tyre doth juſtly puniſh now, in ſuffering
<hi>Herod</hi> to be <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> a denouncer of warre againſt the Tyrian and Sido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian pride.</p>
                  <p>Remember Tyre, you long agoe were given of God for your Idolatry to <hi>Aſers</hi> tribe,
<hi>Ioſh.</hi> 19. <hi>v.</hi> 29. your Idolatry doth ſtill remaine, for which God ſuffers
<hi>Herod</hi> now to threaten warre upon you.</p>
                  <p>Remember Tyre and Sidon, how that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Chriſt vouchſafed to come to you:
<hi>Mat.</hi> 15. when never a Tyrian nor Sidonian would vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to come to him: but only a Syro-phenician, dwelling neere; whoſe daughter was ſo piteouſly perplexed with a devill. Now therefore hee hath delivered you into <hi>Herods</hi> hands, <hi>Deus impios per
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16076:11"/>impios punit,</hi> God puniſheth ſinners by ſinners grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then themſelves; the Idolatrous Iſraelites by more Idolatrous <hi>Nebuchadnezer:</hi> the proud mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileſſe Tyrians by <hi>Herod,</hi> that was more mercileſſe then they.</p>
                  <p>They that are prime in Gods favour, ſhall bee prime in puniſhment too, if they prove unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full unto God: the Tyrians have praeheminence in both, and therefore in the method of Gods re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, the warre is principally againſt the Tyrian towne; againſt the Tyrians and Sidonians and principally againſt the Tyrians <hi>Herod</hi> caries a moſt bloody minde.</p>
                  <p>Nay Tyre, you ſhall have judgement to a ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple now, you boaſted that your chapmen were as rich as Noble men in other countryes were: By what men ſinne, they ſhall be puniſht by the ſame: by chapmen did you ſinne, by chapmen ſhall you be puniſht; here is a chapman for you, but in a Nobler kinde; if ye will joyne all together to make a good reward, <hi>Blaſtus</hi> ſhall mediate your peace unto the King. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> So much of the Tyrians and Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donians. Now of their action.</p>
                  <q>But they came all with one accord unto him.</q>
                  <p>But who acquaints them with the diſpleaſure of the King? Likely ſome meſſenger did advertiſe them of the Kings deſigne, ſome ſummons or ſome pretenſive claime there was. A Kings wrath is like the roaring of a lyon, ſaith <hi>Solomon. Prov.</hi> 19.12. Now a lyons roaring is but a proem to the devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16076:11"/>of the next good prey he meets: and the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der he roares, the greater is the preparation of his ſtomack to devoure: So is the fury of a King. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours therefore muſt not looke for much diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the cauſe, but preſently appeaſe the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure that's begunne: and therefore they came all with one accord unto him: They came, and they came all; and they came all with one accord unto him.</p>
                  <p>Unanimity is the Kingdomes wall and weale. Not like a heard of furious bulles that turne their heads one againſt another; but like the muſick of the Lute, where all the ſtrings harmoniouſly agree: ſo come they now with one accord.</p>
                  <p>It ſeemes it was a popular eſtate; and that the Citizens had all their voices in matters of ſo great a conſequence, as was the conſultation of peace and warre, ſuch was the cuſtome of <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> time, <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>politic. cap.</hi> 14. and here, ſome hundreds of yeares after that. They came with one accord.</p>
                  <p>And yet the cities came not all abroad, but men ſelected for the embaſſie of peace; The whole Kingdome may be ſaid to doe, whatſoever is done by eligible men.</p>
                  <p>Embaſſadors and agents are of antient right: and muſt be able to perſwade or to diſcuſſe a cauſe, and they by their embaſſadors came with one accord and perſwaded
<hi>Blaſtus.</hi> They are come then, but not yet admitted into the preſence of the King.</p>
                  <p>Kings live in greater ſtate then Free Cities doe: there is no treating with them, unleſſe ſome great Internuncio be made your friend: therefore they
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16076:12"/>perſwade <hi>Blaſtus.</hi> Arch-Prophet <hi>Nathan</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe of old did not enter into <hi>Davids</hi> preſence, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till ſome great attendant had preinformed the King: 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 1.23. Nor here the Embaſſadors of Tyre (to preſerve the ancient honor of the Jewes Court:) dare once preſume without the mediati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Blaſtus</hi> to enter the preſence of the King: But they came with one accord, and having per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded <hi>Blaſtus,</hi> the Kings Chamberlaine, one of, or one over the Kings Bebchamber.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Blastus" type="section">
                  <head>But who may this <hi>Blaſtus</hi> bee?</head>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in greeke, in Latin <hi>Germen,</hi> is a branch or yong twigge in our Engliſh tongue: it ſkills not greatly what the name, but what the nature and office of the man imports: his office was <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> either one of the Kings bedcham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, or one over the Kings bedchamber, either Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voſt over the whole chamber (as the Imperiall or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is) or elſe one of the Chamber to his ſacred perſon: it is uncertaine which, for <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in office will beare both ingreek: But certaine it is, that he was very neare and very deare unto the King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: ſome prime bedchamber man, at leaſt, it may be of his ſecret Councell too: ſuch as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> calls <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in the 2. of his <hi>Polit.</hi> and 5. chap. men ſurpaſſing others in qualities laudable, and fit for Courts: Some ſtreine it to the Treaſurer or Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary of State, becauſe they have alwayes free ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe to the preſence of the King: but that cannot ſo properly be here, for they are neither of them
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16076:12"/>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> neither directly over, nor directly of the Kings bedchamber; as here <hi>Blaſtus</hi> was: ſayes my learned councell of interpreters upon the text:</p>
                  <p>Illuſtrious Princes have many noble ſervants, wiſe in the worlds eſteeme, and gracious in their maſters eyes: of this ſort <hi>Blaſtus</hi> was. The matter they propound was faire, and advantageous to the King, as well as to themſelves: So <hi>Blaſtus.</hi> hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the mediator of their peace.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Courtier juſtified a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all his adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries; Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, Greek and Latin.</note>But O noble <hi>Blaſtus</hi> I finde thee much accuſed: a Jury of interpreters have conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned thee for a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted man, I am aſhamed to name them, there are ſo many of them: wel oyled with gifts thou under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſt the cauſe, they ſay, or elſe thou wouldſt not ſpeake a word. But which of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can prove it to be ſo? Why might not <hi>Blaſtus,</hi> being great in office, noble in diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of nature, (as his very name im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports) and prudently foreſeeing, that the matter might be wel accorded both for the Kings purpoſe &amp; the Tyrians future good, of his meere goodneſs, rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of covetouſneſs undertake the cauſe? Or if he had a large reward, yet ſhould not their words be larger the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his fee! if he had a large reward; yet it is excuſable, becauſe the laborer is worthy of his hire; eſpecially in ſo good a cauſe as peace! If he had a large reward; yet the more excuſable it is becauſe the Tyrians and Sidonians were very rich, &amp; very well able to beſtow it upon him: rapacious Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, and proud inhabitants of Tyre; long had their unrighteous riches audaciouſly offended God: yet <hi>Blaſtus</hi> doth take none, but what they doe moſt affectionately perſwade him to accept: and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16076:13"/>therefore ſtill the more laudable it was; for they perſwaded
<hi>Blaſtus</hi> ſaith the text: <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and they perſwading <hi>Blaſtus</hi> of the Kings Bed-Chamber.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="persuasion" type="section">
                  <head>Perſwading.</head>
                  <p>So that he was neither pragmaticall nor cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt: not pragmaticall; to undertake the cauſe till he was perſwaded to it: nor yet corrupt; to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake it for any thing ſo much as for perſwaſion, when once he ſaw the goodneſſe of the cauſe! and therefore to argue more ſtrongly ſtill from the plaine text it ſelfe; which is the end of all contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie: if really and indeed <hi>Blaſtus</hi> had a large re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; yet ought not any living man to ſay it was ſo: becauſe the Scripture uſeth a more mollifying phraſe; and only ſaith; he was perſwaded to it. The moſt ſacred Spirit of the text thus teaching the rudeneſſe of the world not to defame a Court: (the derogation doth redound to the Prince him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe:) but to ingratiate their manners with all candidneſſe of ſpeech; he ſayes not, that they corrupted, but they perſwaded <hi>Blaſtus.</hi> What then the very language of the holy Ghoſt names a meere perſwaſion, how dares the rudeneſſe or the envy of inferiour men call that very ſame thing corruption? <hi>And they perſwading</hi> Blaſtus.</p>
                  <p>You know that honour may invite, juſtice may require, yea want of ſafety may neceſſitate a man to have a ſuite at Court: For woe to the oppreſſed if they might not have recourſe unto their King! yet more then woe if their mediators be ignoble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded men: Miſerable is he, that dealeth with a
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16076:13"/>grype: twice miſerable that with a propitious foole: but thrice lamentable, that meets with both in one: if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ch vices creepe into a Court, the Court creeps out of honour by it: But God be thanked here is no ſuch cauſe of
<hi>Blaſtus</hi> to complaine: in <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> evill Court <hi>Nehemiah</hi> he was good: in <hi>Ahaſhuerus</hi> evill Court <hi>Mordecay</hi> he was good: &amp; in <hi>Herods</hi> evill court why might not <hi>Blaſtus</hi> here be good? Doth not our Saviour ſay? <hi>Bleſſed are the peace makers. Mat.</hi> 5. thrice bleſſed then thou <hi>Blaſtus</hi> art: thy feet more beautifull, then others faces are; becauſe thou bringeſt tidings of glad peace: that by thee the Tyrians dare to move, what by themſelves they never durſt to doe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of peace: <hi>And perſwading</hi> Blaſtus, <hi>who was of the Kings Chamber, they deſired peace.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A friend at Court is worth a Kingdome at ones neede; the Kingdome of Tyre and Sidon: and more then that; he is worth the ſaving of ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſoules: rivers of blood and moſt abhorred death had likely been the end of all; if <hi>Blaſtus</hi> had not interceded for them!</p>
                  <p>How much more good may Courtiers do then men of meaner place; if they would imploy their utmoſt power! The Tyrians, they had loſt their lives; and <hi>Herod,</hi> he had been the more condemned if <hi>Blaſtus</hi> had not beene!</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Blaſtus</hi> their friend; Patron both of their goods and lives! by his breath now they live! <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>And having perſwaded</hi> Blaſtus, <hi>they deſired peace.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>poſtulabant pace<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>:</hi> So much of their mediator; now to the ſubſtance of their petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſelfe; which was peace: <hi>they deſired peace.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:16076:14"/>
                  <p>Peace is the faire ornament both of Church and Common-wealth: peace is the lawfull profit of the whole World: peace the deſirab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> pleaſure both of man and beaſt: Therefore they deſired peace.</p>
                  <p>The Tyrians in eſtate being very rich; and in freedome, richer then eſtate; might have beene richer in pride then in freedome; and ſo have ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogantly replied, wee are unuſed to ſerve; nor will wee now begin. But weighing well their ſuffrances of old; they now deſired peace.</p>
                  <p>Happy they whoſe former warres can make them at the laſt deſirous of a peace, more happy they that can deſire it without a war, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> they deſired it.</p>
                  <p>But by what meanes do they obtaine it? Is the King ſo ſoon appeaſable a man, as to grant it upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſo ſmall deſire? How ſmall? To pay ſubmiſſion is a dearer rent, then are ten thouſand millions by the yeare: heroick ſpirits count it ſo; though baſe do not: which maketh <hi>Solomon</hi> ſay, <hi>Prov.</hi> 25. <hi>v.</hi> 15. <hi>A ſoft anſwer breaketh the bones:</hi> ſo that as he, whoſe bones are broken cannot riſe up to be revenged upon you: no more can he, whoſe minde is appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with a ſoft anſwer: they both ſit ſtill; as if they were eqnally well appayed. Renowned <hi>Solomon</hi> thou haſt bleſt my wearie bones with ſweeteſt ſleepe by that ſweet phraſe of thine; and taught us all great angers to appeaſe by ſoft anſwers and ſubmiſſive deeds. For they perſwading <hi>Blaſtus</hi> did humbly deſire peace; &amp; obtained it of a furious King. Thus their ſubmiſſion did prevaile ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:16076:14"/>their mediator more; being in favour with the King<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> their time and place as much as both: for wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oyes in feaſts and triumph are on foot, anger leaves boyling then: and ſo they tooke the King at Caeſarea; where playes were ordained to Caeſars honour, there <hi>Herod</hi> cloathed beyond him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, ſtrove not to exceed the Nobles, but the very ſun in richnes of attyre; as if owing more, more he would performe to Caeſars honour, then <hi>Phaebus</hi> ſhould himſelf: time and place do much facilitate a ſuite: there they prefer their petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; obtain their ends. Peradventure ſome other conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was in the articles of peace: what? did they buy their peace, ſo ſome Interpreters co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceive: why not? undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Aſa, Ioas</hi> &amp; others by their publique treaſure did redeeme their Kingdomes peace, 1. <hi>K.</hi> 15.2 <hi>K.</hi> 12. So might the Tyria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s here by ſummes of money, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities of wares, or by other gratificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s intreat the peace: better loſe a part then all; of honor, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, or whatſoever elſe it be: their ſcituation ſo commodious was, that traffick would eaſily reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the charges of their peace: whereas expence of war might chance to ruine all: therefore they preferre an unjuſt peace before the juſteſt warre: that could but pinch a while; but this for ever might undoe them all: we Merchants are thought they; &amp; therfore we deſire not totry our right by force of Armes: wee live by free trading into eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part: if warre begin, traffique will end with us; and ſo penury conſume us all: for our borders are but narrow; our fields a barren ſoyle; great mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of people to be maintained by it; more
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16076:15"/>then our ſelves are able to relieve; our corne and chiefe proviſion comes day by day from our neighbours Countrey, the Country of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e Jewes; the juriſdiction under Caeſar is in <hi>Herods</hi> hand; if he in his diſpleaſure ſhall proclaime a warre; nay if but forbid the exportation of corne alone; the famine will conſumeus all: and that is the maine reaſon we deſire peace; becauſe our Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try is nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſht <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> by the Kings Countrey. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſervedly or no; we come not to diſpute: <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rods</hi> diſpleaſure is incurr'd; &amp; his offended counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance we cannot beare; for we live by alimony fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him: that is the reaſon we deſire peace, becauſe our Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try is nouriſhed by the Kings Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try. But wil the King hearke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſuch terms, as thoſe? for it is not out of love, but of neceſſity, that yee ſeek a peace: and ſuch a peace how long wil it laſt, do yee think?</p>
                  <p>Each Kingdome hath ſomething that another needs: The pearling pride of Tyrian ware may pleaſe <hi>Herod</hi> no leſſe then <hi>Herods</hi> corne doth them. Beſides, the time may come; that <hi>Herod</hi> may need their ſhipping, as much as they doe now his corne: moreover what one kingdome wants, that another by the law of nature is bounden to ſupply; or elſe neighbour Kingdomes would for ever be at wars: &amp; <hi>Herod</hi> unleſſe he be a devill unſatiable in malice; having paſſed his royall word, will ſuffer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy their peace: however, they muſt take it <hi>de bene eſſe,</hi> if not <hi>de mero eſſe;</hi> becauſe the greater part if not the whole country receive their alimony from the Kings country.
<hi>And they perſwading</hi> Blaſtus <hi>deſired peace becauſe their Country was nouriſhed by the Kings Country!</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:16076:15"/>
                  <p>Needs muſt they ſtoope, whoſe ſinewes ſhrink for want of meat: famine makes ſtately men ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit their proudeſt necks to Tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts feete: No man ſo ſtrong, but famine will make weake: what the Grecian Captaine ſaid of old, the Tyrian; they ſay here: againſt a man man may prevaile, but againſt nature no man can: and ſo they ſtoope.</p>
                  <p>It is juſtice, that without command they yeeld ſome retribution unto him, by whom they receive nouriſhment; but if it be commanded once, it is juſtice with neceſſity then; which is a ſtronger band: and that's the reaſon why they ſtoope, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are nouriſht by the Kings Countrey; and becauſe they are commanded to ſtoope, or elſe they ſhall feele the power of <hi>Herods</hi> hand; and know; that they are nouriſhed by the Kings Countrey.</p>
                  <p>So I have done with the hiſtorie of the Text; the conjecturall doctrines and the generall appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations ariſing from it.</p>
                  <p>Now there are two ſpeciall applications remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning concerning our owne Kingdome, our owne time, and our own perſons too: the one a laudative; the other an inſtructive part.</p>
                  <p>The laudative is for thankſgiving unto GOD. Awake yee ſleepie Saints; yee mellow duſt of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors awake, you that on Neginoth and Gitteth doe excell; whoſe breaſts have long been purified in hallowed earth; come all to <hi>Davids</hi> quire; and let us ſing lowd prayſes unto him; that gives us Kings; ſweet Kings of peace; by whom your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens children doe live and die in joyfull peace.</p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:16076:16"/>
                  <p>And you all you, the flower of Engliſh blood; that doe enjoy theſe fruits of peace: quailes and manna in every field, nectar and ambroſia under e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very vine; the marrow of the land, and oile of ſeas, Neptune your foole, and Ceres your ſervant is, the gods of the heathen are become your ſlaves; whileſt the God of gods is become your friend, and gives you Kings of peace, by whom you live and die in peace.</p>
                  <p>To the ſcared temple then I ſay come all away, make up the Quire! higher and higher ſing prayſes unto God; untill he find himſelfe well pleaſed with gentle thankes for ſuch his more then gentle favor unto all, in giving Kings and times of peace.</p>
                  <p>And you ſweet ſiſter Church of Tyre and Sidon that doe border neere; whoſe land is nouriſht part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the Kings, keepe this day ſacred with our ſelves, make up the Quire: higher and higher ſing praiſes unto God until he find himſelf wel pleaſed with more then humble thankes for ſuch his more then gentle favour to you all in giving you ſo grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a neighbour King a King of peace.</p>
                  <p>No fuming <hi>Herod,</hi> no froward <hi>Rehoboam</hi> He, no <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, no war-braind man, but <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> a man, whoſe wiſedome ſtudies nothing more, then how he may make peace. As his Father was, ſo is hee; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> a peace maker with all kingdomes round about, and why? But that every one may enjoy your owne ſweet pleaſurable peace at home. Were there a King of alchimy; the warres would eat him up, could all your braziers turne their pewter into gold, yet the warres would eat them up: nay were
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:16076:16"/>all your faces as hard as adamant it ſelfe, yet the warres would bruiſe them to pieces like a potters veſſell. Your rings and jewels, your ſilkes and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous tokens, your chaines of gold and books of rare delight; nay your religion it ſelfe, and all would be made but a ſpeedy prey unto the bloody foe. Now ſilver flocks of ſheep, and ſmoother heards of cattell, your generous horſes and your palaces of State, troopes of revenues and curioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of wares, your religion and the very love of God himſelfe, they are all your owne, becauſe yee enjoy Kings and times &amp; mediators of your peace. Great is the bleſſing of peace amongſt us, oh that our praiſes were as great as it! Wonder many doe, that of all nations we ſhould enjoy ſuch peace, wonder ſhould I as well as they, if there were not an haereditary benediction in it: for of peaceable parents do peaceable children proceed: as his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was ſo is he: a man of peace! nay a maker of peace! Doe we attribute it then altogether to the race? not ſo neither, but chiefly unto God, the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver both of the race and peace! a race may faile, but never God! Ceaſe wee to wonder then, the God of peace doth love our land, and therefore bleſſeth us with Kings and times of peace, no <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> but <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> is our King. Let us in thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe live peaceably at home, love we our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, as Chriſt the King of peace loved us, have peace with all men as much as in us lyes: not for the belly ſake, as the Tyrians with King <hi>Herod</hi> had; but for our Saviours ſake, who would wee ſhould have peace with all. He is worſe then <hi>Herod</hi> that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:16076:17"/>will not entertaine a peace, when faire conditions offer to him; he is worſe then a Tyrian, that will not ſeeke for peace, when as the Kings diſpleaſure is proclaimed againſt all that bring diſturbance to the Church or State, and when as nor they nor we can long be nouriſht without the pleaſure of the King. For he is a King of peace, and thereby doth moſt juſtly intitle himſelfe unto a kingdome grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then our owne, For the moſt Chriſtian King is he, who imitateth moſt our Saviour Chriſt, who is the prince of peace. For ſo ſuffered he the tares among the wheat, till harveſt come, the ripeneſſe of ſeaſon that ſhall root out all. Yet if any offended have, there be many <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> neare and deare unto the King, many gentle mediators, that will procure their peace.</p>
                  <p>Or if you will not render thankes to God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you enjoy the bleſſing of ſuch a King, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe your mediators are as good as <hi>Blaſtus</hi> was: yet render thanks, becauſe your land more happy is, then was the Tyrian and Sidonian ſoile: You are not nouriſht by other countries ſo much as they by you, they ſend to calk your ſhips, you feed their bowels with the fineſt wheat. Their ſilkes and ſtuffes may pleaſe you well, but never nouriſh you ſo much as your owne warme native cloth can do; the enliving reſtaurative of decaying heat. Their fruits and ſpices pleaſe your taſt, but wholeſome juycie meat engenders purer blood to nouriſh any body, then all their ſpices doe, and in ſuch meate doth our Kingdome moſt copiouſlie abound above them all; Therefore, render praiſe to God. For
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:16076:17"/>there the emphaſis is, at nouriſhing, not at pleaſing, your kingdome is pleaſed, but it is not nouriſht by any other kingdome ſo much as by your owne. Therefore render thankes to God, and pleaſe your owne King, you are in better caſe then ever the Tyrians and Sidonians were. Some, if they durſt, would ſay, what need this pleaſing of him? Yes die power moſt juſtly is in him: Among the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes two of the aediles might export their corne, as they thought fit; but with us the command is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together in one mans hands, and ſo he may undoe a forreiner, and pleaſure his owne without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trole, whenſoever he ſhall pleaſe. Wherefore ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his providence hath given you good liberty to uſe, worthily and wiſely do you enjoy your peace, leaſt falling into the power of cruell men, with doubtfull ſighes and groanes in vaine yee often doe deſire the liberty you loſt. But if with pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and thankſgiving you receive the preſent peace, you doe invite the Lord to give you grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter joy. Nor <hi>Origens</hi> ſepulcher nor <hi>Caracalla's</hi> tombe, nor many a future monument beſide had ever ſo famous been at Tyre; if thus they had not well preſerved their peace. Wherefore give thanks for the Churches and the Kingdomes peace; they ſhall proſper that love them both.</p>
                  <p>So much of the Laudative. The Inſtructive ſhall conclude.</p>
                  <p>Though your Country be nouriſht by no other earthly princes land, yet by the King of heavens country it is, take heed then how ye diſpleaſe that King, the King of heaven and earth, the King of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:16076:18"/>kings and God of gods, the ſuper-ſupreme com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander of all things, for by his countrey wee are nouriſht every one: as how? or why? Heaven and earth are all his countrey, the ſea, and all to blaſt, to blight, to burne, to drowne, or how hee pleaſe. But how ſhould wee diſpleaſe him then? or who knowes that he is diſpleaſed? O the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion! The plague continues blew amongſt us, the famine hath begun to whet her hungrie teeth, the Cataracts of heaven are let looſe: drie <hi>aries</hi> into watry <hi>piſces</hi> changed, the ranſome of a King into the ſubjects ruine, for military <hi>March</hi> is made a ſtanding poole: All theſe are more then ſignes that the King of kings is highly diſpleaſed with us, and doe you aſke then who knowes that he is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed with us? or what the cauſe is, that hee is diſpleaſed, doe you aſke? When as our ſinnes ſo ſuperabundant are, what marvell if he drowne your corne with immoderate ſhowres in the field to puniſh thoſe that drowne their braines with immoderate drinking in the houſe? What marvell if he ſuffer wheat to be miſcaried at ſea, to puniſh thoſe by land that miſimploy their wheate? What wonder if he deſtroy all nouriſhment of corne, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then it ſhould nouriſh a company of vagrant impes, that nothing but travell from ſigne to ſign, and never ſcarce received the Sacrament in all their lives? What wonder if he raiſe the price of corne to puniſh thoſe that raiſe the price of rents and wares? In ſumme, what marvell if our corne faile us, when wee faile God in the good employment of our corne? Among a thouſand of thoſe miſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:16076:18"/>ſcarce one will ſpeak twelve ſyllables of grace in thankes to God for the greateſt meale or other plenty that ever he received; but ſweare, forſwear, curſe, ſteale, riot, and domineere under every ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer ſigne, as if they were the onlie men, by whom the King and kingdome did ſubſiſt, whereas indeed they are a diſhonor to the King, confuſion to the kingdom, the off-ſcowring both of men &amp; beaſts, and the very ſcumme of all the land. I feare there are ſome thouſands of thoſe Aegyptian beggars that never were baptized. So that drunkenneſſe, glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony, fraud, covetiſme, the unworthy receiving, or not receiving of the Sacraments, and a million more are all in cauſe, why God denies this fruitfull alimonie, which formerlie he gave. And doe we then aſke what is the cauſe? when as our ſinnes ſo ſuperabundant are. Beleeve not me, but S. <hi>Baſil,</hi> and the word of God it ſelfe.
<hi>Deut.</hi> 28.23. <hi>Baſil, Hom.</hi> 7. <hi>to:</hi> 1. The heavens are turned to braſſe, becauſe our foreheads are; and the earth to iron, becauſe our ſelves are iron-hearted both toward God &amp; man: There is no pureneſſe in the heavens, becauſe there is no pureneſſe in our lives, in the cloudes we walk, and in the cloudes we ſpeake, by darkneſſe of cariage and by miſtineſſe of words men doe obſcure the very elements of Juſtice, as the cloudes doe them, by non-baptiſing water is the ſeed of the unbaptiſed moſt juſtly deprived of harveſt ſeed: The nature of their ſinnes hath changed the very nature of the yeare: The bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of ſinnes hath taken the burthen of ſheaves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way: laſt yeare the windineſſe of faith and light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:16076:19"/>of religion hath made a light harveſt amongſt us, and this yeare as if the cloudes were conjured all together to do a miſchiefe to us, what a deluge have they threatned us of late. And how ſhall we appeaſe this hungry anger of our God? ſaith zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Saint
<hi>Baſil</hi> in the forecited place. You know what will offend him, well enough, and what will pleaſe him too, yee know: Will any wiſe man then provoke a Princes wrath? decline it rather he ſhould, as mariners doe a ſtorme. <hi>Procul à love &amp; fulminibus</hi> live farre from offending Jupiter, or elſe he wil thunderbolt you unto death: how much farther then from provoking the God of <hi>Iupiter?</hi> will any man digge for wilde fire with a ſword? the word is too light, will any man digge for hell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire by ſuch an high provoking of his God? If not, then leave all well knowne, rude, notorious ſinnes. Did the Idolatrous dedicat a part to forrein Saints did the drunkard to his folly, the wanton to his luſt, the witches to the Devill himſelfe give the dedication of the laſt yeares corne? therefore this yeare they ſhall have none to eate themſelves, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they leave theſe provocations, and dedicate all to God, to grace, and vertuous actions of the State; God will conſume both the corne and them. Curſe nothing either of your owne or others, leaſt God bring a curſe upon you and the whole land for it. Blot out the names of greivous uſurers out of your townes: the earth ſhall yeeld you the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter uſurie of corne. Drunkards, theeves, oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, be they never ſo great, let them be of ſmall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimation with you; poore widowes, fatherleſſe, or
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:16076:19"/>whatſoever elſe, let them be of ſmall or no reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, unleſſe they be godlie poorer: eſpecially the Aegyptian troopes of unbaptized vagrants, that are borne, no man knowes where. Poore ſoules, how might they live in happineſſe againe, if corne were but as cheape as once it was! But they offer ſcorne and abuſe both to God and man, ſo ſoone as ever things are cheape, nay to this very houre they boaſt, that they can make bread of beanes, of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cornes, nay of knots of ſtrawes rather then they will ſtarve. O miſerable! what if they can? will they therefore provoke the Lord? can they make bread of iron or drink of braſſe? If not, be ſtill then and know, that the God of Scripture will be true, and if you ſtill proceed to challenge him by ſuch epidemicall ſinnes, as hitherto yee have, he will turne your heavens to iron &amp; your earth to braſſe: <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.23. And as ſoon ſhall <hi>Dives</hi> make <hi>Lazarus</hi> bring him water to coole his tongue in hell, as you ſhall make drinke enough of braſſe to quench your dropſey thirſt.</p>
                  <p>Yee Nobles and rich men of the land; if poore men will not reclaime themſelves; yet doe yee ariſe and goe to God for peace! You are all nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſht by the King of heavens country, aſwell as they; nay more then they, by how much more you doe enjoy: But you think you have not ſo much need, as they! yes; I will ſhew you how! the curſe will light on you, though they unworthy be: for with greater freedome might you eat; if plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty were on all: but now not ſo, the want of others redounds as ſinne to you: as <hi>Lazarus</hi> to <hi>Dives</hi> did:
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:16076:20"/>Beſides conſider well, how honourable a bleſſing to your Kingdome it were, to live in peace with God; and plenty among all: how dangerons if o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe! Famine, of all humane calamities the chiefe, doth miſchiefe that, which ſwords and ſhipping could never ſpoile; and though your e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies ſeeme to ſleepe a while, as <hi>Herod</hi> did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale his lurking ſpleen, till famine had circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented them of Tyre; but when deareneſſe of corne aroſe, then aroſe his wrath; and what by ſea he never durſt, by famine now he dares to doe in threatning them a warre: ſo will your enemies do to you, thereaten and conquer too; if the King of heaven withdraw his nouriſhing hand: Tis not the poore, but rich mens goods they ſeeke! and rich and poore and all muſt yeeld, when famine comes: Publique neceſſity hath no law, but to the Lawgivers mercy onely muſt it ſue for conditions of peace becauſe your Countrey is in all things nouriſht by the King of heavens countrey.</p>
                  <p>Rich and poore; unleſſe wee be fooliſher then the Tyrians were, with feathered and ſolicitous ſpeed ſhould we this day procure our peace from God, they theirs from
<hi>Herod</hi> but a mortall man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their country was nouriſht by <hi>Herods</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey: and is not ours much more by Gods? nor can we any way endure his offended ire! blaſt us by warre, blaſt us by famine, by ſpungie clouds and by tempeſtuous haile, by ſcorching ſummers and ſnowie winters hee may empoveriſh us how and when he pleaſe, though warre do not ariſe, yet if he do but with-hold his nouriſhing hand,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:16076:20"/>within a yeare or two wee ſhall be utterlie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done; becauſe our Countrie in everie thing is nouriſht by the King of Heavens Countrie: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by all the meanes of Chriſtendome let us ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licite our peace with Him, the King of Kings and God of Gods: Sea, Land, Aire, Waters, Windes, Starres, Angels good and bad are all at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand: ſubmit to him, as the Tyrians to King <hi>Herod</hi> did: confeſſe he hath beene more gracious to us, then ever wee to him, be heartily ſorrowfull for everie tranſgreſſion that is paſt, faſt and lament for offending him, that faſted fortie daies for you: and when you faſt, give a charitable part of that you ſpare unto the poore; leaſt otherwiſe it bee thought you faſt to ſave charges more then ſave your ſoules: henceforward drinke for ſtrength and not for wantonneſſe, for hunger eat, and not for luſt: correct the rudeneſſe both of your owne and others ſinnes: in everie thing give thankes to God, performe himdaylie ſervice for whatſoever you enjoy: bleſſe everie thing yee do converſe withall: live ſweeter, newer, freſher in graces, then the ſpring it ſelfe in flowers is: ſuppoſe God be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed more then <hi>Herod</hi> was, he wil be eaſier plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed too: joyne wee all with one accord, as here the Tyrians did: go all to <hi>Blaſtus;</hi> make him the media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of our peace: <hi>If any man have ſinned we have an advocate with the Father</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Iohn:</hi> Wee have a <hi>Blaſtus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Eſay; germen de radice Ieſſe:</hi> a branch of the root of Jeſſe:
<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> a Lordlie <hi>Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> indeed: Mediator both for Church and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, there is one neare and deare enough
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:16076:21"/>unto the King of Heaven himſelfe: who is gone before to make our peace, to prepare our ſeverall manſions, and gently to uſher us into the preſence Chamber of the great King, even Jeſus Chriſt the righteous, and he is the propitiation for all our ſinnes: goe all with one accord to him: the prayers of a Kingdome ſhall be ſooner heard, then of a ſingle man: beſeech him humbly to mediate all your peace: tis all but one the forgiveneſſe of ſinnes: You therefore for me, and I for you, and each and all for one another make ſupplication unto him; ſo to pacifie his fathers ire, ſo to enwiſe and envertue us all with future grace, that wee never may offend him or his Father any more; becauſe our Kingdome is nouriſhed in every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular by the King of Heavens Country.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <closer>To the ſame God the Father, and his only Sonne Ieſus Chriſt, and to the holy Ghoſt bee all honor &amp; glory world without end. Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:16076:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
